<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: transcriptions | davidcel.is]]></title>
  <link href="http://davidcelis.github.io/blog/categories/transcriptions/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://davidcelis.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-05-10T09:55:46-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://davidcelis.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[David Celis]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Your Ex-Lover Is Dead (Stars)]]></title>
    <link href="http://davidcelis.github.io/blog/2011/07/12/your-ex-lover-is-dead/"/>
    <updated>2011-07-12T01:35:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://davidcelis.github.io/blog/2011/07/12/your-ex-lover-is-dead</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is one of my favorite songs. Back in 2005, Canadian Indie band Stars released this song as a single. In 2007, they released another album aptly entitled <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Do_You_Trust_Your_Friends%3F"><em>Do You Trust Your Friends?</em></a> full of remixes by, well, their friends. Well-known artist <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Owen_Pallett">Owen Pallett</a>, then known as <a href="http://www.dominorecordco.com/uk/news/18-12-09/final-fantasy-name-change-to-owen-pallett/">Final Fantasy</a>, took it upon himself to arrange this song for piano, vocals and strings.</p>

<!--more-->


<p><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=x4cZyF2i5yw">YouTube video of the song</a> (Owen Pallett’s version)</p>

<p><a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=r5Or6-HOveg">The original Stars version</a></p>

<p>This is a song I really wanted to learn to play on the piano and sing. Usually I’m great at picking things up by ear, but the orchestra playing along with the piano made it difficult in this case. I decided to see if there was any sheet music that had been printed for the song. Unfortunately, I found only a single, unofficial transcription that pretty much sucked. I got fed up and decided to transcribe it myself. I think I did a really good job, and I’m fairly sure it’s at as accurate as it can be.</p>

<p>So, without further ado, <a href="http://dl.dropbox.com/u/94814/Slingshot/Pictures/Your%20Ex-Lover%20Is%20Dead%20(Final%20Fantasy).pdf">this is my transcription</a> for Owen Pallet's version of "Your Ex-Lover Is Dead" by Stars for piano and vocals. As far as I can tell, it's extremely accurate. Here's a video so you can hear how it sounds before you play it yourself.</p>

<div class="video-container">
  <iframe width="" height="" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/1A7fp6gI0b8 " frameborder="0" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe>
</div>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
